James Terry Collection, 1733-1815
Connecticut Historical Society
James Terry Collection
1733-1815
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Terry, James
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
James Terry, born in Terryville, Connecticut, was the oldest son of James Terry, the founder of the Eagle Lock Company. His great-grandfather was Eli Terry, the founder of the clock industry in Connecticut. James Terry was a man of many interests. After working in his father’s factory, he entertained more intellectual pursuits. He collected books and manuscripts, researched and excavated sites of prehistoric humans in the West, and conducted a study of early libraries in the thirteen colonies. He led the anthropology department of the American Museum of Natural History from 1891-1894, after which he moved to New Haven, Connecticut. He was a life member of the Connecticut Historical Society.
Scope and Content
The collection was donated to the Historical Society on December 4, 1894. In 1903 they were bound into two volumes. With another volume of material from a different donor, the collections were known as the Separate Church Papers. At a later date the documents were disbound and their page numbers from their respective volumes were noted in the upper left hand corner. The documents retain their page number order, which is roughly chronological.
In various scholarly works, the Separate Church Papers were cited as the James Terry Collection. Confusion over the inconsistent citations and catalog records, plus the discovery of the second collection, led to reprocessing and recataloging.
The records primarily represent activities of the Separate, or Strict Congregational Church in Canterbury, Connecticut, the first of its kind formed in the state. The Separate Church developed from schisms within the Congregational Church, namely about infant baptism, paying taxes to support the established church and calling pastors.
The small group of Separate Churches in the state kept in close contact for support. Churches in other parts of the state wrote to Canterbury to invite their members or a delegation to attend days of fasting and prayer or the ordination of a new minister. Or they consulted the Canterbury church on matters of doctrine and practice, the very issues that had created the schism originally.
Records of the church itself include minutes of meetings and a copy of the covenant. Among the most interesting minutes are those in which members are accused, examined and then either censured or excommunicated for inappropriate behavior. There are also minutes for meeting in which delegations from the Congregational Church and the Separate Church attempt reconciliation.
Other items of interest in the collection are a petition to the Connecticut General Assembly regarding Liberty of Conscience, a copy of “Ye Burden of Dissatisfaction by Hezekiah Spencer of Somers, a minister’s response to questions posed by the church in the process of finding a new minister, and proposals to, minutes of, and the Articles of Confederation for the Convention of Strict Congregational Churches in Connecticut.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Terry, James, 1844-1912.
Subjects
Strict Congregational Church (Canterbury, Conn.); First Congregational Church (Canterbury, Conn.); Separatists --Connecticut.; Dissenters, Religious --Connecticut.; Great Awakening.; Canterbury (Conn.: Town) --Church history --18th century
Contents:
- Papers
  - Records, 1733-1734 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Records, 1735-1744 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Records, 1744-1745 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Records, 1746-1748 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Records, 1748 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Records, 1749-1750 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Records, 1750-1751 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Records, 1751 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Records, 1751-1752 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Records, 1752 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Records, 1752 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Records, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Records, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Records, 1753-1754 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Records, 1754-1755 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Records, 1756-1764 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Records, 1764-1766 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Records, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Records, 1767-1769 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Records, 1769-1772 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Records, 1771-1773 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Records, 1773-1778 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Records, 1779-1780 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Records, 1782-1783 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Records, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Records, 1783-1784 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Records, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Records, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Records, 1784-1785 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Records, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Records, 1785-1786 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Records, 1786-1788 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Records, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Records, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Records, 1789-1790 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Records, 1791-1815 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Records, undated (Box 1, Folder 37-40)